On the air. Unaware.
The Truman Show is a comedy, drama film directed by Peter Weir.
An insurance salesman begins to suspect that his whole life
is actually some sort of reality TV show.
Truman Burbank, played by Jim Carrey.
Meryl Burbank / Hannah Gill, played by Laura Linney.
Marlon / Louis Coltrane, played by Noah Emmerich.
Lauren Garland / Sylvia, played by Natascha McElhone.
Angela Montclair / Alanis Montclair, played by Holland Taylor.
Christof, played by Ed Harris.
The Truman Show is a 1998 American comedy-drama film written and
co-produced by Andrew Niccol, and directed by Peter Weir.
The film depicts the story of Truman Burbank (played by Jim Carrey), a man who is unaware that he is living his entire life on a colossal
soundstage, and that it is being filmed and broadcast as a reality television show that has a huge international following.
All of his friends, family, and members of his community are paid actors whose job is to sustain the
illusion and keep Truman unaware that the world he inhabits is scripted and fake.
The film's supporting cast includes Laura Linney, Ed Harris, Noah
Emmerich, Natascha McElhone, Holland Taylor and Paul Giamatti.
Niccol's original spec script was more of a science-fiction
thriller, with the story set in New York City.
Producer Scott Rudin purchased the script and set up
production at Paramount Pictures.
Brian De Palma was to direct before Weir signed on as director, making the film
for $60 million—$20 million less than the original estimate.
Niccol rewrote the script while the crew was waiting for Carrey to sign.
The majority of filming took place at Seaside, Florida, a
master-planned community located in the Florida Panhandle.
The Truman Show held its world premiere in Los Angeles on June 1,
1998, and was released in North America on June 5.
The film was a financial success, grossing $264 million worldwide, debuting to critical acclaim, and earned numerous nominations
at the 71st Academy Awards, 56th Golden Globe Awards, 52nd British Academy Film Awards, and 25th Saturn Awards.
The Truman Show has been analyzed as an exploration of simulated reality, existentialism, surveillance, metaphilosophy, privacy, and reality television, and described as a
genre-blending work that features elements of dystopian fiction, meta fiction, psychological drama, romantic comedy, satire, and social science fiction.
The film explores themes of escape, paranoia,
dystopia, suspicion, video surveillance.
The tone is lighthearted and emotional.